Guide to the Records of the Dean of Women, Washington Square College, Dorothy McSparran Arnold 1924-1962 RG 19.3
New York University Archives
Records of the Dean of Women, Washington Square College, Dorothy McSparran Arnold
1924-1962
RG 19.3
New York University Archives
2.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
The Arnold Papers are the administrative files of Dorothy McSparran Arnold who served as the Advisor to Women's Office (1924-28), Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (1928-48), and Dean of Women (1948-61). Arnold was the administrator responsible for women's interests at Washington Square College for forty-three years. The collection includes her administrative files with minutes, correspondence, memoranda, printed material, news clippings that describe, and photographs that illustrate her activities on behalf of women students.
Office of the Dean of Women.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
The Papers of Washington Square Counselor to Women Students, Dorothea Berger.
Elmer E. Brown Chancellor's Papers.
Munn-Recht, Aristine (1st Dean of Women)
The Student Affairs Collection
Women at NYU - Archives H
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series.
Scope and Content Note
The Arnold Papers describe the evolution of the counseling and programming system Washington Square College developed to coordinate students' intellectual growth with their development as social and moral beings. The papers also reveal the growth of strong women's organizations at the college and present some insights into the attitudes toward women and their roles. Washington Square College, set in an urban environment with a large commuter student body, valued and promoted the extracurricular customs of undergraduate life. Societies and sororities, athletics, undergraduate class loyalties and clubs were community builders. Student activities created the illusion of a society in miniature, preparing the student for citizenship and building loyalty and friendships at the college.
As the College grew in size, the Dean's Office became formally responsible for assuring the academic and personal advisory roles faculty had handled in less complex times. These responsibilities were gradually divided. The academic counseling, remaining under the authority of the Dean's office was assigned to teaching faculty. The 'official' social and personal counseling became the preserve of faculty (and later student affairs specialists) removed from active teaching. Student activities and counseling became the business of the administration rather than the faculty. Mrs. Arnold made the switch from teaching to student affairs administrator in 1924 and her career spanned the next forty-three years.
The papers have rich material on women's organizations at the College. The League of Women and the Eclectic Society records cover over thirty years (1920's-50's) giving early organizational information on the group's activities, membership and selection. The Junior Advisory Committee and Faculty Advisory Corps records offer a view of the college's academic and peer counseling programs. There is limited material on fraternity/sorority relations and freshman orientation in the thirties and fifties. Information on the decline of women's athletics is in several folders of the Faculty Advisory Board (1929-1958).
Records of the Student Committee on Educational Policy (1947-59) indicate the shift to give students a more important role in college governance. An important theme throughout the papers is the constant fight Dean Arnold waged for money for adequate facilities and programs for women. The annual reports, the building office file and the athletic files reveal the struggle. Mrs. Arnold's interest in linking college women to national organizations and interests appear in the American Association of University Women and Mortar Board files.
Dean Arnold's values and her relationship with students are elusive in the official files but appear indirectly in folders on the organization of Alumni functions, in news clippings files on students and administrators and in the honorary society and junior advising committee folders. The restricted folders containing the results of Dean Arnold's counseling sessions with students are more revealing. They deal with individual students physical, moral and emotional problems and contain her personal reactions and decisions.
Few interests beyond Arnold's official duties appear in the files. She maintained files on the cases of two New York University victims of the 50's political paranoia, Edwin Berry Burgum and Lyman R. Bradley. Burgum, a tenured member of the English department was dismissed by the Chancellor after refusing to testify before the McCarran Committee in 1952. Bradley, convicted of contempt for refusing to surrender the records of Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee to the House committee, was temporarily suspended and removed from the chairmanship of the German department. Their files include newsclippings from local and university newspapers, news releases, student announcements and protests and Bradley's defense pamphlet. There is also a subsidiary file on Communists, including a copy of Sidney Hook's article on fellow travellers. The files appear to have been culled and are incomplete. Inexplicable gaps of years occur in many folders. The files of Arnold's successor, Dorothea Berger duplicate, overlap and seem to incorporate some of Arnold's: Arnold, Papers files. (see: Judson Residence, University Christian Foundation, Association of Women Students, Loeb Student Center, Gamma Gamma Sigma, Parker, Pan-Hellenic and Junior Advisors folders) The files may have been mixed at one time. The Berger papers and Arnold papers should be regarded and consulted as complementary collections.
The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject or correspondent. Each folder is arranged chronologically with the earliest date at the front of the folder. Photographs are filed within appropriate folders.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Dorothy McSparran Arnold (? - 1971) received a B.A. from Cornell University in 1918. She was a professor and administrator at Washington Square College for forty-three years. Arriving in 1924 as a young instructor in the English department, Arnold found a ten-year old college with a strong commitment to women's undergraduate education. A year after her arrival she became involved in the other side of college life - the development of the student's social and moral character. She went into student affairs. During the 1925-26 school year, Mrs. Arnold began her work as a counselor and administrator for women students at Washington Square College. She was named chairman of the faculty committee on women's interests and, as the catalog for that year states: "matters affecting the interests of girls in the college should be referred to Mrs. Arnold."
Her activities ranged over all aspects of student life. The next year she became the official Advisor to Women. In December of 1928, the Council appointed Mrs. Arnold an Assistant Dean, recognizing her as an administrator. She had received her academic promotion to Assistant Professor in 1926 and continued to perform the role of women's advisor without change in salary.
She continued as an Assistant Dean until November of 1948 when she became Dean of Women. She reported directly to the Dean of Washington Square College and had jurisdiction over women students' physical, social and moral well-being. She served as Dean until her retirement in 1961. As Advisor and Dean, Mrs. Arnold was concerned with promoting the welfare of women students. She worked with the students, providing continuity, structure and the development of new programs for women. In addition to extensive personal counseling, she served as--the active advisor to most of the campus' women's organizations. Her office organized or coordinated many of the activities of the League of Women, women's honorary and social societies and women's athletics. She was also effective in developing a peer-counseling program to aid freshwomen and transfer-students' adjustment to college life. The Junior Advisors Committee, under her direction, was an important resource for newcomers and a place to recognize out-standing junior women. The League of Women, the Eclectic honorary society and Pan-Hellenic Council were other vehicles for recognizing and developing women student leaders.
As an administrator Mrs. Arnold worked for women students, providing representation on college committees directly concerned with student issues. She was a member of the Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, Faculty Committee on fraternities and sororities connected with the Student Committee on Educational Policy, various scholarship committees and the committee on faculty-student advising. She was also an advisor on disciplinary, and financial aid matters. As a Dean she participated on college and university governance committees; the Cabinet of the College, Advisement Council and the Council of Deans.
As a woman administrator before feminist ideas took root, Mrs. Arnold was frequently assigned (or assumed) non-academic responsibilities presumably suited to the "special touches" a woman could provide. The organization of public social occasions and social service projects fell on her shoulders. She ran Red Cross Blood Drives, alumnae/i Christmas parties, mother-daughter teas, and the Art Competition. She was also in charge of the administration and decoration of the lounges.
Mrs. Arnold was the women students' official advocate in the administration. She was both nurturer and authority figure. She was also the college's housekeeper and hostess. How did her roles affect women students' lives and her influence within the college's administrative structure? Her papers present more questions than the answer. Dean Pollock once said "It took three people to replace her" because of the overwhelming amount of responsibility that she executed from day to day. She was respected by her colleagues for her fairness, firmness and good taste. She helped shape the college experience of hundreds of women and its impact on the college is still unexplored.
Dean Dorothy McSparran Arnold died on November 22, 1971.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Provenance
Dean of Washington Square and University College, New York University
Arnold, Dorothy, (Dorothy McSparron Arnold); Berger, Dorothea; Bergum, Edwin Berry; Bradley, Lyman R.; Gamma Gamma Sigma (Association of Women Students).; New York University.; Washington Square College. Eclectic Society.; Washington Square College. League of Women.; Washington Square College. Student Committee on Educational Policy.; Washington Square College. Women's Office.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Minutes.; New York (State) |z New York.; New York University |x History.; New York University |x Societies.; Photographs.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science |x Faculty |x Women.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science |x Students.; Washington Square College |x Administration.; Women's rights.
- Series I
  - Advisement Council, correspondence., 1937-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1945-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Advisement Council, minutes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Advisory Corps (Faculty), correspondence., 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Advisory Corps (Faculty), minutes, 1950, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumnae Club, report, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1938-1942, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alumni Federation, announcements, 1958, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alumni Saturday, correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Association of University Women, correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - A.A.U.W. (See Above) correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - A.A.U.W., correspondence, 1953-1955, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Red Cross, Blood Bank, correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Red Cross, Blood Bank, 1950, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports to the Dean, 1934-1935, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art Competition at Washington Square, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, Minutes, rules, plans, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    General note
    Also called Board of Control for Women's Athletics
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Name changes to "University Board of Athletic Control for Women's Athletics," Dec. 1938.
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for, Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's - Athletics, 1956, minutes, correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - B - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bradley, Lyman R.; report, printed material, (see also clipping file), 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Building Office, correspondence, memos., 1950-1955, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Burgam, Edwin Berry; printed material, reports, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cabinet of the College (Washington Square), 1928, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cabinet of the College (Washington Square), Minutes, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Council of Deans (All-University), Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Eclectic Society, Membership List, Constitution, Report, Minutes, 1922, 1935-1936, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Eclectic Society, Minutes, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Eclectic Society, Eligibility lists, membership, correspondence, 1947, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Eclectic Society, Eligibility list, selection materials, correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Eclectic Society Dinners, correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Personal File S-Z, Correspondence, memos, 1944-1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    RESTRICTED MATERIALS